Boker tov בוקר טוב, Boker tov, chodesh tov חודש טוב. chodesh tov.
Today's daf דף daf is nun chet נח, nun chet, 58. We
pick up from the middle of nun zayin amud bet נז עמוד
ב. nun zayin amud bet. We had just read the important Aggadata
אגדתא Aggadata about these young children throwing themselves into the sea to
save themselves from a life of sexual abuse and so on and
immorality and very important Aggadata אגדתא Aggadata that serves for the Tosafot
תוספות Tosafot as an indication of a rabbinic attitude towards like sometimes
even taking one's own life could be an appropriate form of Kiddush
Hashem קידוש השם Kiddush Hashem as opposed to the standard halakhic discourse
which mean our cases of allowing martyring yourself and allowing your life
to be taken but as Tosafot תוספות Tosafot points out you're not
always given that choice. Anyway so in that in mind now the
Gemara גמרא Gemara continues with another similar such story. Okay
and now the Gemara גמרא Gemara says like this:
V'aleihem hakatuv omer ועליהם הכתוב אומר V'aleihem hakatuv omer we pick up
about 20 lines from the bottom. The line starts with the word
L'toch hayam לתוך הים L'toch hayam it's like right underneath the Gilyon
HaShas גליון הש״ס Gilyon HaShas in the right hand margin. V'aleihem hakatuv
omer ועליהם הכתוב אומר V'aleihem hakatuv omer regarding these young children the
verse says Ki alecha horagnu kol hayom כי עליך הורגנו כל היום
Ki alecha horagnu kol hayom for you God we have been slaughtered
the whole day nechshavnu k'tzon tivcha נחשבנו כצאן טבחה nechshavnu k'tzon tivcha
like sheep to the slaughter. Rabbi Yehuda omer רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi
Yehuda omer now Rabbi Yehuda says this verse Zo isha v'shiva baneha
זו אשה ושבעה בניה Zo isha v'shiva baneha a woman and her
seven children. Asyuvei kamay
d'keisar אתיוהו קמיה דקיסר Asyuvei kamay d'keisar they brought the first child
in front of Caesar. Amru lei אמרו ליה Amru lei they said
to him palach l'avodat kochavim פלח לעבודת כוכבים palach l'avodat kochavim serve
idolatry. Amar lehu אמר להו Amar lehu katuv batorah כתוב בתורה katuv
batorah Anochi Hashem Elokecha אנכי ה׳ אלהיך Anochi Hashem Elokecha no I
can't says I am the Lord your God. Afku v'katlu אפקוהו וקטלוהו
Afku v'katlu so they took him out and executed him killed him.
Asyu l'idach אתיוהו לאידך Asyu l'idach kamay d'keisar קמיה דקיסר kamay d'keisar
they brought child number two in front of Caesar. Amru lei אמרו
ליה Amru lei palach l'avodat kochavim פלח לעבודת כוכבים palach l'avodat kochavim
worship idols. Amar lehu אמר להו Amar lehu katuv batorah כתוב בתורה
katuv batorah Lo yihyeh lecha elohim acherim al panai לא יהיה לך
אלהים אחרים על פני Lo yihyeh lecha elohim acherim al panai don't
have other gods. Afku v'katlu אפקוהו וקטלוהו Afku v'katlu they took him
out and killed him. Asyu l'idach אתיוהו לאידך Asyu l'idach number three.
Amru lei אמרו ליה Amru lei palach l'avodat kochavim פלח לעבודת כוכבים.
palach l'avodat kochavim. Amar lehu אמר להו Amar lehu katuv batorah כתוב
בתורה katuv batorah Zoveach l'elohim yochoram זובח לאלהים יחרם Zoveach l'elohim yochoram
anybody who worships foreign gods will be banned will be destroyed. Afku
v'katlu אפקוהו וקטלוהו Afku v'katlu they took him out and killed him.
Asyu l'idach אתיוהו לאידך Asyu l'idach number four. Amru lei אמרו ליה
Amru lei palach l'avodat kochavim פלח לעבודת כוכבים palach l'avodat kochavim worship
idols. Amar lehu אמר להו Amar lehu katuv batorah כתוב בתורה katuv
batorah Lo tishtachaveh l'el acher לא תשתחוה לאל אחר Lo tishtachaveh l'el
acher don't worship another god. Afku v'katlu אפקוהו וקטלוהו Afku v'katlu they
took him and killed him. And Asyu l'idach אתיוהו לאידך Asyu l'idach
they took the fifth one. Amru lei אמרו ליה Amru lei palach
l'avodat kochavim פלח לעבודת כוכבים. palach l'avodat kochavim. Amar lehu אמר להו
Amar lehu katuv batorah כתוב בתורה katuv batorah Shema Yisrael Hashem Elokeinu
Hashem Echad שמע ישראל ה׳ אלהינו ה׳ אחד. Shema Yisrael Hashem Elokeinu
Hashem Echad. Afku v'katlu אפקוהו וקטלוהו Afku v'katlu they killed him. Asyu
l'idach אתיוהו לאידך Asyu l'idach number six. Amru lei אמרו ליה Amru
lei palach l'avodat kochavim פלח לעבודת כוכבים palach l'avodat kochavim worship idols.
Amar lehu אמר להו Amar lehu katuv batorah כתוב בתורה katuv batorah
V'yadata hayom vahasheivota el levavecha וידעת היום והשבת אל לבבך V'yadata hayom
vahasheivota el levavecha notice that we're switching from the lo ta'asehs לא
תעשה׳ס lo ta'asehs to the positive affirmations of faith. You shall know
and put to your heart ki Hashem hu ha'elokim bashamayim mima'al v'al
ha'aretz mitachat ein od כי ה׳ הוא האלהים בשמים ממעל ועל הארץ
מתחת אין עוד. ki Hashem hu ha'elokim bashamayim mima'al v'al ha'aretz mitachat
ein od. Afku v'katlu אפקוהו וקטלוהו Afku v'katlu okay they took him
out and killed him. Asyu l'idach אתיוהו לאידך Asyu l'idach number seven.
Amru lei אמרו ליה Amru lei palach l'avodat kochavim פלח לעבודת כוכבים
palach l'avodat kochavim worship idols. Amar lehu אמר להו Amar lehu katuv
batorah כתוב בתורה katuv batorah Et Hashem he'emarta hayom את ה׳ האמרת
היום Et Hashem he'emarta hayom God you have chosen today v'Hashem he'emircha
hayom וה׳ האמירך היום v'Hashem he'emircha hayom God has chosen you today
so we're going from an affirmation of faith to the point not
only do we affirm God as our God but God actually is
you know affirms us as his nation and will not abandon us
even in this time of tragedy or oppression. Kvar nishbanu l'Hakadosh Baruch
Hu כבר נשבענו להקדוש ברוך הוא Kvar nishbanu l'Hakadosh Baruch Hu she'ein
anu ma'avirim oso b'el acher שאין אנו מעבירים אותו באל אחר she'ein
anu ma'avirim oso b'el acher we swore to God that we will
not exchange him for another god v'af hu nishba lanu ואף הוא
נשבע לנו v'af hu nishba lanu she'ein ma'aviru l'umah acheret שאין מעביר
אותנו באומה אחרת she'ein ma'aviru l'umah acheret he won't exchange us for
another nation. Okay so Amar lei keisar אמר ליה קיסר Amar lei
keisar ishdi lach gushpanka אישדי לך גושפנקא ishdi lach gushpanka so now
the Caesar was getting a little fed up and it was number
seven so he's got to he's going to try to get something
accomplished with number seven threatening them to kill them is not enough.
So he says listen here's what I'm gonna do. Ishdi lach gushpanka
אישדי לך גושפנקא Ishdi lach gushpanka I will throw for you my
coin that has my image on it v'shaklei ושקליה v'shaklei bend down
to pick it up and to return it to me ki heichi
d'leimru כי היכי דלימרו ki heichi d'leimru and people will see this
and they'll say kablu alei harmuna d'malka קבלו עליה הרמונא דמלכא kablu
alei harmuna d'malka you're accepting upon yourself the authority of the king
because you're bowing down in my presence also bowing down to my
image so at least it'll make it look like you're worshipping me
which obviously makes it clear that the avodah zarah עבודה זרה avodah
zarah that they're trying to get them right is the sort of
you know is the cult of the what's that called the imperial
cult or the cult of the emperor right that they that they
made him as a god. So it's also the worshipping of the
Caesar as god. Okay so. Amar lei אמר ליה Amar lei chaval
alecha keisar chaval alecha keisar חבל עליך קיסר חבל עליך קיסר chaval
alecha keisar chaval alecha keisar woe to you Caesar
woe to you Caesar. Al kvod atzmecha kach על כבוד עצמך כך
al kvod atzmecha kach if you're so makpid מקפיד makpid on your
honor al kvod Hakadosh Baruch Hu al achat kamma v'kamma על כבוד
הקדוש ברוך הוא על אחת כמה וכמה al kvod Hakadosh Baruch Hu
al achat kamma v'kamma how much more so do you think God
is makpid מקפיד makpid on God's honor? So how could I therefore
you know betray the honor that I have to show God and
I can't even make it look like I am betraying that. Afku
l'miktalei אפקוהו למקטליה Afku l'miktalei they took him out to kill him.
Amra lehu immei אמרה להו אמיה Amra lehu immei so the mother
said to them the Roman soldiers havunee lee v'anshkei purta הבו לי
ואנשקיה פורתא havunee lee v'anshkei purta give him to me
let me at least like kiss him a little bit. Amra lehu
אמרה להו Amra lehu she said to him banai בני banai my
children so I guess havuhu הבוהו havuhu give them to me so
even though they said they took him out to be killed presumably
this is in the plural so presumably it means they took him
out to be executed but they haven't been killed yet so she
went and she spoke to all of her children before they were
executed. Go say to Abraham your forefather, אתה עקדת מזבח אחד, Atah
akadata mizbe'ach echad, you offered up one sacrifice. Okay, actually it's just
interesting, מזבח אחד, mizbe'ach echad,
like זבח אחד. zevoch echad. One wonders if they switched it to
מזבח mizbe'ach to be a little bit less, you know, directly saying
that Isaac was slaughtered, right, so they make it an altar and
and I mean מזבח mizbe'ach is a different form of זבח. zevoch.
I don't know, but anyway, do they translate that as altar or
as sacrifice? I mean by context, you offered up, it doesn't make
sense, right?
You bound up one altar?
ואני עקדתי שבעה מזבחות. Va'ani akadeti shivah mizbachot.
So it seems like it's really saying altar. Yeah, but it doesn't
make sense obviously grammatically it really is like one sacrifice. But now,
but and I'm offering up seven. אף היא
עלתה לגג ונפלה ומתה. Af hi altah legag venafalah u'metah. She also
went up to the roof and fell and died. יצאה בת קול
ואמרה אם הבנים שמחה. Yatzah bat kol ve'amrah em habanim smeichah. The
mother of the children rejoices. They gave up their names for שם
השם. Shem Hashem.
Now of course, we recited that in הלל. Hallel.
There you go. Now, now this again is very powerful in the
writings of the Crusade and the Crusade chronicles and the imagery there
about invoking Abraham as a model for sacrificing oneself and not only
oneself, one's children for God. And in the Crusades, parents were afraid
that when the sort of Christian Crusaders surrounded the town and they
were afraid that they were going to be forced to convert, so
at least they felt that maybe they could give up their lives,
the adults, and not convert, although that also they might have been
tortured and might feel that they couldn't resist. But the children, right,
they would be taken as infants and they would be brought up
as Christians and there would be nothing they could do to save
them. So they actually went ahead and slaughtered their children, took their
children's lives and then killed themselves. Exactly, you know, did this but
actually actively took their children's lives. And they evoked the עקידה Akeidah
because the עקידה Akeidah is the active or the attempt to actively
take the life of a child, right, in the name of God.
You know, one of the most tragic ends of this was that
somebody did this and then the something happened and then the Christians
actually left and then the, you know, and then the tragedy never
took place, so wound up having, you know, done this horrible thing,
you know, and then the Crusaders never actually wound up like, you
know, attacking the town. But but often they were, you know, most
of the time they did wind up attacking and killing and forced
conversions and so on. But then the Jews there for fear of
that were taking this active participation, right, which raises these profound halakhic
questions, right, not only taking your own life, taking another person's life,
a child's life and so on. And evoking essentially in in the
Crusade chronicles they put in the words of some of those people.
You never know if it's like poetic rewriting. This was written actually
by one of the survivors, but you still never know if it's
an actual accurate, fully accurate account or a little bit of a
poetic retelling. But they put in the words of some of one
of the people exactly this, that a father is saying or a
mother is saying like, you know, Abraham offered up one sacrifice, I'm
offering up all of my children as sacrifices and so on. The
other thing about this is it plays on a מדרש Midrash which
actually has that Abraham actually did offer up Isaac, because Isaac was
never slaughtered in the פשט pshat of the פסוקים, psukim, right, but
if you read the פסוקים psukim also, it says that Abraham actually
returned and it doesn't say that Isaac returned. So actually that leaves
an opening for the מדרש, Midrash, right? You remember a מדרש Midrash
that says, and I'm way digressing now, but give me one more
minute, the מדרש Midrash that says you might know a מדרש Midrash
about the אפר של יצחק מונח לפני ה׳, eifer shel Yitzchak munach
lifnei Hashem, like the ashes of Isaac are before God on the
altar up in heaven, there's like a famous מדרש Midrash about that.
So one basically what that's playing on is that Abraham didn't slaughter
Isaac, right? It says אל תשלח ידך אל הנער. Al tishlach yadcha
el hana'ar. But
what we forget about is is that there was a fire on
the altar. So according to the מדרש, Midrash, he didn't slaughter him
and he just let the fire consume him. And he actually Isaac
actually was offered up and then a miracle happened and his ashes
were reconstituted and he came back alive and so on. So anyway,
this is an actual מדרש. Midrash. So anyway, the point is is
that these imagery, both the imagery of אברהם אבינו Avraham Avinu and
this story, right, served as this powerful model. I mean I'm not
saying that they read this גמרא Gemara and they said, oh what
a good idea, obviously it was started by this profound religious intuition
that we can't do, we have to do anything to stop us
or our children being forcefully converted, right, and then it and but
then it served as this model to articulate, you know, that concept.
And here of course in this story, she killed herself but she
never ended up killing the children. And it's interesting that the story,
you know, uses the word מזבח mizbe'ach instead of זבח. zevoch. I
think to a little bit shift it from sort of the direct
statement that they were actually sort of slaughtered as a sacrifice. Yes.
Just in, Steinsaltz changed it to עבודה זרה avodah zarah not עבודת
כוכבים. avodat kochavim. Okay. Second this is in this, this is Rav
Yehuda introducing it. It was during his lifetime that Roman emperors started
deifying themselves during their lifetime. Oh interesting.
Prior to that, during
the תנא Tanna period, they... Yeah,
so מצדה Masada story doesn't normally get quoted, but the מצדה Masada
story is an earlier yeah.
They did know about.
I mean, it's in Josephus, I don't know if it's in the
pseudo-Josephus that the ראשונים Rishonim had access to, the the Hebrew יוסיפון,
Josippon, which wasn't really Josephus, it was a pseudo-Josephus. I don't know
if it was there, but that doesn't get quoted, like this gets
quoted and the אברהם Avraham gets quoted. Okay. Okay. רבי
יהושע בן לוי אמר Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi amar זו מילה שניתנה
בשמיני. zu milah shenitnah bashmini. This idea of we're going back now
to the פסוק pasuk of כי עליך הורגנו כל היום, ki alecha
horagnu kol hayom, we've been slaughtered every day, it's for the ברית
מילה brit milah that now now the idea of ניתנה בשמיני, nitnah
bashmini, I'm not exactly sure the tie, why he emphasizes that, but
it means that often they would, you know, מילה milah would be
one of the things that the Romans would forbid, especially because it's
a defiguring of the body and so on and there often the
Jews would be prepared to risk their lives in order to do
a ברית מילה. brit milah. Okay, רש"י Rashi says a little differently,
sometimes since it's an operation, sometimes there could be complications and the
child could die, but I don't think so, I don't think we're
trying to frame the basic מצוה mitzvah of מילה milah as כי
עליך הורגנו כל היום. ki alecha horagnu kol hayom. I think we're
trying to say that sometimes they would give up their or risk
their lives for מילה. milah. רבי שמעון בן לקיש אמר Rabbi Shimon
ben Lakish amar אלו תלמידי חכמים שמראים הלכות שחיטה בעצמן. elu talmidei
chachamim shemarim hilchot shechitah be'atzman.
Okay, actually כי עליך הורגנו, ki alecha horagnu, it's a bizarre shift
from this emphasis of the oppression and the Romans. This is when
you're learning הלכות שחיטה hilchot shechitah and you want to show, well,
let me show to you how actually you would do a שחיטה,
shechitah, so you take a real knife and you say, you see,
you put it on the animal's neck like this and you move
the knife like this and then you slip a little bit, so
that's כי עליך הורגנו כל היום. ki alecha horagnu kol hayom. We're
so, we're so passionate about תלמוד תורה, talmud torah, sometimes we get
carried away and we don't realize what we're doing. I have no
idea that's such a bizarre juxtaposition. Anyway, okay, as דאמר רבא d'amar
Rava כל מילי לחזי איניש בנפשיה בר משחיטה. kol milei lachzei inish
b'nafshei bar mishechitah.
You can demonstrate anything on yourself
except שחיטה. shechitah. Do not try this at home. So, but what
is interesting, you know, is it is like shifting, if you think
about the whole רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai story,
by shifting from the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash to תן לי יבנה
וחכמיה, ten li Yavneh v'chachameha, all of a sudden we have this
this huge shift of the of the camera, as it were, from,
you know, חורבן הבית churban habayit and the the Caesar and the
and the martyrdom to like, oh, you're in the בית מדרש beit
midrash and you're demonstrating הלכות שחיטה. hilchot shechitah. Right? A complete shift
to that world of תורה torah now that can replaces this other
world in which this פסוק pasuk had a very different meaning. Now
it has a meaning in the world of תורה. torah.
So, okay,
בר משחיטה bar mishechitah ודבר אחר vedavar acher and another matter, which
is, I assume, means רש"י Rashi says צרעת ומראות נגעים. tzara'at umar'ot
nega'im. Don't sort of demonstrate, you know, the
how like a leprosy looks on your body because, I guess, you
don't want to actually directly put leprosy on your body but that's
like an עין הרע ayin hara type of a thing. Okay, contagious?
Well, yes, but how I mean oh I guess if you demonstrate
it like you actually bring a leper in, but that's if that's
if we're talking about actual
leprosy. Okay. רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar
אלו תלמידי חכמים שממיתים עצמם על דברי תורה. elu talmidei chachamim shememitim
atzmam al divrei torah. And now we shift from the literal death
to a figurative one. כי עליך הורגנו כל היום ki alecha horagnu
kol hayom means that we give we kill ourselves over learning תורה.
torah. Like, you know, we we, you know, we just like אדם
כי ימות באוהל, adam ki yamut b'ohel, right? We spend all of
our energies, there's a self-sacrifice involved in the learning of תורה. torah.
So again, that's a real nice sort of way of a transformation
of what this בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash literal martyrdom, giving up your
life, כי עליך הורגנו כל היום ki alecha horagnu kol hayom to
a תורה torah centered
figurative type of a כי עליך הורגנו כל היום. ki alecha horagnu
kol hayom. כדריש לקיש k'de-Resh Lakish דאמר ריש לקיש d'amar Resh Lakish
אין דברי תורה מתקיימין אלא במי שממית עצמו עליהם. ein divrei torah
mitkaymin ela bemi shememit atzmo aleihem.
They only are established somebody who's willing to give sort of die
over it, figuratively, שנאמר shene'emar זאת התורה אדם כי ימות באוהל. zot
hatorah adam ki yamut b'ohel. This is the תורה, torah, person's willing
to die in the tent of the תורה. torah. אמר רבה בר
בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi
Yochanan back back to חורבן הבית, churban habayit, ארבעים סאה קציצי תפילין,
arbaim se'ah ktzitzai tefillin, 40 סאה, se'ah, which is like a large
measure, of תפילין tefillin בתים, batim, okay,
קציצה ktzitzah is like a בית, bayit, not the straps but the
בית bayit of תפילין tefillin בתים batim נמצאו בראשי הרוגי ביתר, nimtze'u
berashei harugei Beitar, found on the heads of those that were slaughtered
in ביתר. Beitar. So you took all their תפילין tefillin and people
would go out, it's also an image right? We forget about this,
but people would wear תפילין tefillin the whole day. So there they
were and also the sense that they're, you know, that they were
slaughtered and, you know, and, you know, with their תפילין tefillin on,
the, you know, the way in which it was a destruction of
the of the people and also of the תורה, torah, you know,
what they
represent. רבי ינאי ברבי ישמעאל אומר Rabbi Yannai berabi Yishmael omer שלוש
קופות של ארבעים ארבעים. shalosh kupot shel arbaim arbaim. It wasn't 40
סאה, se'ah, it was three huge... containers each one of forty סאה
*seah*, three times as much. במתניתין תנא *bematnitin tana* in a ברייתא
*braita* we taught ארבעים קופות של שלוש שלוש *arbaim kupot shel shalosh
shalosh*, forty containers of three סאה *seah*. Okay. ולא פליגי *velo pligi*
and they don't debate, meaning not the forty times three or the
three times forty. רש"י Rashi: *Rashi* says this means the first version
which was forty or the second version which was three times forty.
ולא פליגי הא דרישא הא דדרא *velo pligi had'reisha had'dara*. It makes
a difference whether it's תפילין של יד *tefillin shel yad* or תפילין
של ראש *tefillin shel rosh*. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says that the תפילין
של ראש *tefillin shel rosh* because you have to make four compartments
you know would wind up being larger because you would just need
to like you couldn't make it as tiny. I don't know if
you've seen this you know about sometimes how tiny some people have
some תפילין *tefillin* like we have nice big תפילין *tefillin* right? But
if you've ever seen or they found תפילין *tefillin* at מצדה *Masada*
you know you have very very tiny. So if you're making it
so tiny and you're trying to make four בתים *batim* like that
you make in של ראש *shel rosh*, you gotta make it a
little bigger just to be able to manipulate something of that size.
So רש"י *Rashi* says that actually would have been three times as
large as the של יד *shel yad*. Yes.
Was forty סאה *seah* the amount required for a מקווה *mikvah*?
Yes, that's actually correct.
40 סאה *seah*.
Oh,
that's interesting. Yeah, maybe there's something symbolic about the 40 סאה *seah*
and the cleansing of that. Yeah, I don't know, I have to
think about that, but that's a good
point. Okay. אמר amar רבי אסי *amar Rabbi Assi* ארבעה קבין מוח
*arba'a kabbin mo'ach*,
so
that was a shift back to again and it's also interesting thinking
about this mixture about מקדש *Mikdash* and תורה Torah *Torah*, right? Oh,
thank you so much. That was a shift from... you really don't
have to do that, just give me a paper cup. I'm sorry.
I don't... anyway, the shift from מקדש *Mikdash* to תורה Torah. *Torah*,
but also the focus we've been focusing on the destruction of the
מקדש *Mikdash* to the destruction of the people. But the thing about
the people with the תפילין *tefillin* on them also refocuses us or
reorients us towards that like תורה Torah *Torah* world, right? You know,
because the תפילין *tefillin* is the מצווה *mitzvah* and it has the
פרשיות *parshiyot* written in it and so on. So it's interesting these
three themes that are a little bit intersecting. Okay. אמר Amar, רבי
אסי *amar Rabbi Assi* ארבעה קבין מוח *arba'a kabbin mo'ach*
now back to the horrific destruction of the people. Four קב *kav*
of brains נמצאו על אבן אחת *nimtze'u al even achat* could be
found even on one stone, right? The smashing of the skulls and
so on just on one stone. עולא אמר Amar, תשעה קבין *Ulla
amar tisha kabbin*, nine קב *kavs*. רב Rav, כהנא ואיתימא שילא בר
מרי *Rav Kahana v'itema Shila bar Mari* מאי קרא *mai kra* what's
the פסוק pasuk? *pasuk*? בת בבל Bavel. השדודה *Bat Bavel hashidudah* daughter
of בבל *Bavel* that is like taken captive אשרי שישלם לך *ashrei
she-yeshalem lach* praised is the one that compensates for you, that pays
back to you, אשרי שיאחז ונפץ את עללייך אל הסלע *ashrei she-yo'chez
venipetz et olalayich el hasala*. Now this is a very like challenging
disturbing פסוק pasuk *pasuk* because it says... this is in actually על
נהרות בבל *Al Naharot Bavel*. I don't know the last time I
said על נהרות בבל *Al Naharot Bavel* before בענטשן *bentching* must have
been at least 30 years ago when I was in summer camp
or something, more 40 years ago. I don't know anybody who has
the time to say על נהרות בבל *Al Naharot Bavel* before בענטשן
*bentching* anyway, but
in על נהרות בבל *Al Naharot Bavel* there's this one פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* because that refers to, thank you, the Babylonian exile, right? And
it says like here you are you've been taken into exile into
בבל *Bavel*, praised is God who will you know pay you back
for everything that you suffered. And then there's this very disturbing פסוק
pasuk *pasuk* which actually was being discussed a lot in or in
some context, right, do you remember the whole thing that came up
a few weeks ago this what's called the bloody wedding the thing
in ישראל Yisrael *Israel* where they had these like you know they
people whatever it was a very deeply disturbing thing about a very
like this bloodlust vengeance demonstrated by פרום *frum* Jews. And this פסוק
pasuk *pasuk* that says praised is God praised is the one who
will compensate you who will smash you know and the you know
the infants the infants of בבל *Bavel* who your oppressors on the
rock. So it speaks about this like you know bloodlust vengeance against
the oppressors. Here it's being quoted as an evidence that if that's
considered to be to pay back obviously that's must have been what
happened to you because right and this is evidence that this is
what happened to the Jewish people. But anyway that definitely is you
know challenging especially in the contemporary ישראל Yisrael *Israeli* context. Okay. בני
ציון benei Tzion. היקרים המסולאים בפז *B'nei Tzion ha-yekarim ham'sula'im bapaz* now
we're going to look at פסוקים Psukim *pesukim* in איכה Eicha *Eichah*
that speak about the destruction a little bit about the first בית
*Bayit* but we're sort of conflating them. ברוך השם *Baruch Hashem*. That's
good. Okay. המסולאים בפז *Ham'sula'im
bapaz*.
So what does this mean? The children of Zion that were dear
that were that were precious, המסולאים בפז *m'sula'im bapaz*.
So what does המסולאים בפז *m'sula'im bapaz* mean? As precious as gold?
Let's see what the word המסולאים *m'sula'im* means. מאי מסולאים בפז mesula'im
bapaz *mai m'sula'im bapaz*? אילימא דהוו מחפיי בפיזי *eileima d'havi m'chapai b'pizi*
maybe it means they were coated in gold covered in gold. ואמר
Ve'amar, דבי רבי שילא *ve'amar de-bei Rabbi Shila* תרתי מתקלי אסתרי פיזי
*tarti matkli istari pizi* two weights... of gold, of a pure gold
נחות לעלמא came down to the world. חדא ברומי chada beRomi one
in Rome וחדא בכולי עלמא vechada bechulei alma the other one was
distributed equally in the whole world. So there's no way that in
Zion all of the kids were completely covered in gold, even a
gold jewelry or whatever. There wasn't, wouldn't be enough gold to go
around. Okay אלא שהיו מגנים את הפז ביופיים ela she-hayu meganin et
ha-paz be-yofyam but that actually means מסולאים בפז mesula'im bapaz.
means that they would be like the, you know, that they would
be more praiseworthy than gold, people would sort of ah what good
is gold jewelry it doesn't look as gorgeous as my kids? Okay
so that's מסולאים בפז. So okay where were we? מעיקרא me-ikara now,
אלא שהיו מגנים את הפז. ela she-hayu meganin et ha-paz. מעיקרא חשיבי
דרומאי me-ikara chashivei de-Roma'ei originally the you know prestigious people in Rome
הוו נקטי בליונא דגושפנקא havu nakti bilyona de-gushpanka they would take an
image of in their like of of a seal, of a like
of a handsome type of a person, an image of that ומשמשי
ערסייתיהו u-mishamshi arsyateihu and when they would have sex they would have
this image of this handsome person on the wall and therefore that
would lead to having good-looking kids because the idea would be that
what you are thinking at the time that you are having sex
affects how the child is conceived. Okay, going back to to some
degree the story about יעקב Ya'akov and the striped things and so
on. So that's how they would have good-looking kids. But מכאן ואילך
mikan ve'eilach from the time they took Israel into captivity so now
we're switching from you know from the first בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
to the second מייתי בני ישראל maiti benei Yisrael they would take
you know Jewish people from the Israelites ואסרי בכרעי דפורייהו ve-asrei be-charei
de-puryeihu and tie them up at the leg of their bed ומשמשי
u-mishamshi they'd have sex and they'd look at these gorgeous young men
and women and that was and therefore their kids would turn out
to be handsome. Okay אמר ליה חד לחבריה amar lei chad le-chavrei
so one person said to his friend הא היכא כתיבא ha heicha
ketiva this is a very you know deeply disturbing type of a
of a punishment to have suffered, you know, of an of to
where is this written prophesied that בני ישראל benei Yisrael would suffer
this type of a thing this degrading type of a thing? So
אמר ליה amar lei he said to him גם כל חלי וכל
מכה אשר לא כתוב בספר התורה הזאת gam kol choli ve-chol maka
asher lo katuv be-sefer ha-torah ha-zot anything that even even something that's
not written is going to happen at the time of exile. So
that's what was written. It was written by this catch-all phrase that
you're going to suffer even types of you know suffering that has
not been heard of before this type of degrading experience. So אמר
so he said back to him כמה מרחקנא מדוכתא דפלן kama mirchakna
mi-duchta de-palan how far was I from getting up to that פסוק?
Pasuk: Like apparently they were learning some section in the תורה Torah
and he said oh that was a good פסוק Pasuk you quoted
me. How far away how far was that פסוק Pasuk. from where
I was learning? So אמר ליה amar lei אינגד פוסטא ופלגא ingad
pusta u-palga basically a page and a half. You were a page
and a half away. You would have gotten up to that פסוק
Pasuk yourself in a page and a half. אמר ליה amar lei
he said to him אי מטאיי לגביה לא אצטריכי לך ei matayei
legabei lo itztrichi lach oh had I gotten a little further in
my reading I wouldn't have had to ask you I would have
gotten to that פסוק Pasuk, and figured it out for myself. Very
distinct exchange asking questions in דף יומי. daf yomi. Very bizarre exchange
anyway. All right maybe lightens things up a little bit. אמר רב
יהודה אמר שמואל משום רבי שמעון בן גמליאל amar Rav Yehuda amar
Shmuel mishum Rabi Shimon ben Gamliel מאי דכתיב mai de-chtiv what's meant
by the verse עיני עוללה לנפשי מכל בנות עירי einai olela le-nafshi
mi-kol benot iri my eyes are like you know mourn over my
soul from all of the children of my people of my of
my city. ארבע מאה בתי כנסיות היו בכרך ביתר arba mea batei
kneysiyot hayu be-krach Beitar there were 400 synagogues in the in the
city of Beitar וכל אחת ואחת היו בה ארבע מאה מלמדי תינוקות
ve-chol achat ve-achat hayu bah arba mea melamdei tinokot each synagogue had
400 obviously these are exaggerated numbers 400 school teachers וכל אחד ואחד
היו לפניו ארבע מאה תינוקות ve-chol echad ve-echad hayu le-fanav arba mea
tinokot and every each one of the school teachers had 400 children
he was teaching של בית רבן
shel beit raban school children וכשהיה
אויב נכנס לשם u-che-she-haya oyev nichnas le-sham and when the enemy would
go in there היו דוקרין אותם בחוטריהן hayu dokrin otam be-chutreihen
they would pierce them with their staffs וכשגבר אויב ולכדום u-che-she-gavar oyev
u-lechadom
and when they were finally they were completely conquered captured כרכום בספריהם
karchum be-sifreihem they wrapped them in their books והציתום באש ve-hitzitum ba-esh
and lit them on fire like the famous story of רבי חנניה
בן תרדיון Rabi Chananya ben Teradyon we focus on the single רבי
חנניה בן תרדיון Rabi Chananya ben Teradyon but this is saying that
this happened to all of these school teachers and school children and
in these synagogues you know very obviously numbers numbers
are way off yeah
obviously the numbers are way off. But you know one also thinks
about the you know obviously about the destructions at the at the
Holocaust. So I mean one cannot help sort of thinking about comparisons.
Yeah yeah. תנו רבנן tanu rabanan מעשה ברבי יהושע בן חנניה ma'aseh
be-Rabi Yehoshua ben Chananya שהלך לכרך גדול שברומי she-halach le-krach gadol she-be-Romi
when story of Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya
he went to the big city of Rome or the big city
in Rome maybe in the Roman Empire but one also imagines it
means Rome. Anyway אמרו לו amru lo תינוק אחד יש בבית האסורים
tinok echad yesh be-veit ha-asurim they said to
him there's one child that we have in the prison יפה עיניים
וטוב רואי yafeh einayim ve-tov ro'i who is of good visage you
know beautiful eyes וקווצותיו סדורות לו תלתלים ve-kvutzotav sdurot lo taltalim his
hair his locks are like in layers so you know sort of
thought that you know you would want to save him because he's
so good-looking going back to the good-looking story before about the בני
ציון. הלך ועמד על פתח בית האסורים halach ve-amad al petach beit
ha-asurim he went and he stood at the entrance of the prison.
By the door of the jail, of the prison. אמר, and he
quoted the פסוק: Pasuk. מי נתן למשיסה יעקב וישראל לבוזזים. Mi natan
limshisah Ya'akov ve'Yisrael le'vozezim. Who has given Jacob for despoiling and ישראל
Yisrael, to בוזזים, bozezim, ישראל Yisrael. over to whatever, despoiling.
אמר אותו
תינוק Amar oto tinok
so that child responded, heard that פסוק pasuk quoted, and he responded
and he quoted the end of the פסוק. pasuk ואמר הלא השם
Ve'amar halo Hashem it is God, זו חטאנו לו zo chatanu lo
we have sinned to God, it's because we have sinned to God.
ולא אבו בדרכיו הלוך Velo avu bidrachav haloch and we have not
desired to go in his paths. ולא שמעו בתורתו Velo shamu betorato
and we did not listen to his תורה. Torah, Okay so he
noticed, he knew the end of this פסוק pasuk in ישעיהו. Yeshayahu.
So אמר,
so who has this? רבי יהושע בן חנניה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya
said, מובטחני בו שימורה הוראה בישראל. Muvtachni bo shemoreh hora'ah be'Yisrael.
I have confidence that he will actually eventually teach תורה in ישראל,
that he's such a young child and he knows and he knows
this פסוק, pasuk you know, he knows how to respond. העבודה, Ha'avodah,
like
which is a sort of a way of taking an oath, שאיני
זז מכאן עד שאפדנו בכל ממון שפוסקים עליו, She'eini zaz mikan ad
she'efdenu bechol mamon sheposkim alav, I will not leave here
until I redeem him no matter how much they ask for him,
which is interesting by the way. Like how, you know, what imagines,
I mean we only know פסוקים Psukim in תנ"ך Tanakh that are
in the הפטרה. Haftarah. But anyway one imagines that they were much
more versant in, conversant in פסוקים psukim in תנ"ך. Tanakh. He didn't
have to be a huge תלמיד חכם Talmid chacham necessarily to be
able to quote the end of the פסוק. So it's a little
interesting that he was so astounded unless תינוק Tinok literally means תינוק,
Tinok, like maybe he was three years old or something, who knows.
Anyway, אמרו לא זז משם עד שפדאו בממון הרבה, Amru lo zaz
misham ad shepda'o bemamon harbeh, he didn't leave there until he redeemed
him with much, with a lot of money. ולא היו ימים מועטים
עד שהורה הוראה בישראל, Velo hayu yamim mu'atim ad shehorah hora'ah be'Yisrael,
and it was only shortly thereafter that he actually taught תורה or
actually, הוראה Hora'ah is not just taught תורה, he like
he ruled, he was a halachic authority in ישראל. ומנו Umanu and
who was this? רבי ישמעאל בן אלישע, Rabbi Yishmael ben Elisha, רבי
ישמעאל בן אלישע. Rabbi Yishmael ben Elisha.
So actually now this raises interesting questions, the fact that he paid
a high price for him, right, you might remember an earlier גמרא
Gemara about תיקון עולם. Tikkun Olam. So let's look at תוספות. Tosafot.
כל ממון שפוסקין עליו, Kol mamon sheposkin alav, so תוספות Tosafot says,
כי איכא סכנת נפשות פודין שבויים יותר מכדי דמיהן. Ki itcha sakanat
nefashot podin shvuyim yoter mikdei dameihen. So this תוספות Tosafot did not
say this earlier, but he says when it said you don't redeem
captives, that's when their lives are not at risk. But if their
lives are at risk, then you'll pay whatever price is being asked,
which we had not heard of earlier. Earlier it just said you
gotta limit it so that it doesn't get out of hand. כדאמרינן
בפרק השולח גבי מוכר עצמו ואת בניו לעובדי כוכבים, Kedamrinan be'perek ha'shole'ach
gabei mocher atzmo ve'et banav le'ovdei kochavim, כל שכן הכא דאיכא קטלא.
kol shekein hacha de'ika katala. אי נמי, Ei nami, so that's one
explanation which is an important qualification of the earlier גמרא. Gemara. משום
דמופלא בחכמה היה, Mishum de'mufla be'chochmah hayah, because he was so brilliant
and he clearly was and he clearly was important, you know, to
the Jewish people, then that would we would make an exception for
him, which is always very interesting, right? Do we make exceptions for
people for their social worth? Right, on the one hand we sort
of like don't like to distinguish like one life for another. On
the other hand there's this משנה הוריות, Mishnah Horayot, right, which is,
כהן קודם ללוי לוי קודם לישראל. Kohen kodem le'Levi Levi kodem le'Yisrael.
Thank you, תלמיד חכם קודם לכולם Talmid chacham kodem le'kulam and so
on. So that is interesting, you know, when that does factor in.
Okay, back to the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay, now here's a story you're all going to know because it's
in one of the famous קינות. Kinot. Okay. אמר רב
יהודה אמר רב,
Amar Rav Yehuda
Amar Rav, מעשה בבנו ובתו של רבי ישמעאל בן אלישע, Ma'aseh bevno
uvito shel Rabbi Yishmael ben Elisha, there's a story about the son
and daughter of רבי ישמעאל בן אלישע Rabbi Yishmael ben Elisha who
are a כהן, Kohen, שנשבו לשני אדונים, shenishbu lishnei adonim, they were
taken captive by two separate masters. One took the boy, one took
the girl. And we've just learned how gorgeous these kids were. לימים
נזדווגו שניהם במקום אחד, Liyamim nizdavgu sheneihem bemakom echad, these two masters
happened to meet up in a bar or something. ואמר, and one
said, יש לי עבד שאין כיופיו בכל העולם כולו, yesh li eved
she'ein kiyofyo bechol ha'olam kulo, I have a slave that you've never
seen anyone with this handsome. וזאת אומרת יש לי שפחה שאין בכל
העולם כולו כיופיה, Ve'zot omeret yesh li shifchah she'ein bechol ha'olam kulo
kiyofyah,
I have a slave woman you've never seen anyone this beautiful. אמרו
בוא ונשיאם זה לזה, Amru bo venasi'em zeh lazeh, hey let's get
them to let's marry them to one another, ונחלק בולדות venachlok bevladot
and then we'll have children that they'll be the most gorgeous children
ever and we'll split them between us. Obviously they're being treated here
like commodities, right? We'll just divide up the children. הכניסום לחדר Hachnisum
lachader and
so they put them into a room. זה ישב בקרן זוית וזו
ישבה בקרן זוית, Zeh yashav be'keren zavit ve'zo yashvah be'keren zavit, one
sat in one corner, one sat in the other corner. זה אמר
אני כהן בן כהנים גדולים, Zeh amar ani kohen ben kohanim gedolim,
I am a כהן Kohen the descendant of כהנים גדולים, kohanim gedolim,
אשא שפחה esa shifchah I'll marry a slave woman? וזו אומרת אני
כהנת בת כהנים גדולים, Ve'zo omeret ani kohenet bat kohanim gedolim, I
am a כהן Kohen woman the daughter of כהנים גדולים, kohanim gedolim,
ואנשא לעבד ve'enaseh le'eved and marry a slave? ובכו כל הלילה Uvachu
kol halailah they cried the whole night. Presumably they couldn't see each
other. כיון שעלה עמוד השחר Keivan she'alah amud hashachar when the sun
rose up, הכירו זה את זה, hikiru zeh et zeh, they recognized
one another, they saw that they were brother and sister, ונפלו זה
על זה וגעו בבכיה, venafalu zeh al zeh vega'u bivchiyah, they fell
on one another, they cried out with a moan, עד שיצתה נשמתן,
ad she'yatzta nishmatan,
their soul departed. So again actually we have a repeating of the
theme of the. giving up of the life, okay, here they did
not necessarily willingly take their lives, but that was somehow seen as
a fitting end that they were you know that they took up
their they gave up their that they lost that they you know
that they died and they didn't have to in the end be
forced to carry this through. ועלייהם כונן ירמיהו ve'alehem konen Yirmeyahu on
them ירמיהו Yirmeyahu mourns על אלה אני בוכיה al eileh ani bochiya
for these I cry עיני עיני יורדה מים. eini eini yordah mayim.
It's I've always wondered about this story, when they said I can't
marry a slave or a slave woman, do they realize that the
other person not that they were their sister, but they were slaves
because they were part of the captivity of the Jews? So that
they couldn't marry a fellow Jew who had become a slave, even
though they themselves had become a slave, is that the story? It's
interesting. Okay, or did they not realize that the other one was
a Jew. Anyway. Okay. אמר ריש לקיש. Amar Reish Lakish. מעשה באשה
אחת maaseh be'ishah achat
is the story of one woman וצפנת בת פנואל שמה veTzafnat bat
Pnu'el shemah her name was צפנת Tzafnat daughter of פנואל. Pnu'el. צפנת
Tzafnat what does the word צפנת Tzafnat mean? שהכל צופים ביופיה shehakol
tzofim beyofya everybody would stare would gaze at her beauty. בת פנואל
bat Pnu'el בתו של כהן גדול bito shel kohen gadol ששימש לפני
ולפנים sheshimesh lifnai velifnim
the daughter of a כהן גדול kohen gadol so another story about
a beautiful woman who was a daughter of a כהן גדול kohen
gadol who would serve in the innermost chambers, that's פנואל Pnu'el the
innermost of God שנתעלל בה שבאי כל הלילה shenitalel bah shavai kol
halaila that the captor
basically raped her the whole night,
took sexual advantage of her the whole night. למחר Lemachar הלבישה שבעה
חלוקים hilbishah shivah chalukim once he was done with her, the next
morning he had her wear seven garments והוציאה למוכרה vehotziah lemochrah
and he took her out to sell her. So now that he
was done. בא אדם אחד שהיה מכוער ביותר ba adam echad shehayah
mecho'ar beyoter one person who was exceedingly ugly came. אמר לו Amar
lo הראני את יופיה hareini et yofyah show me her beauty. אמר
לו Amar lo he said to him ריקא reika empty one אם
אתה רוצה ליקח קח im atah rotzeh likach kach if you want
to buy buy.
שאין כיופיה בכל העולם she'ein kiyofyah bechol ha'olam כולה. kulah. אמר לו
Amar lo אף על פי כן af al pi chen
even so I want to see her. I want to see her
naked, I want to see her beauty. הפשיטה ששה חלוקים hipshitah shishah
chalukim he stripped her of six of the garments והשביעי vehashvi'i and
the seventh one קרעתה ועמדה karatah ve'amdah she herself tore off ונתפלשה
באפר venitpalshah be'afar and she rolled herself in the dust. אמרה לפניו
Amrah lefanav and she said to God רבונו של עולם Ribono shel
olam אם עלינו לא חסת im aleinu lo chasata if you don't
have compassion on us על קדושת שמך הגיבור למה לא תחוס al
kedushat shimcha hagibor lamah lo tachos why won't you have compassion on
your greatness. ועל זה כונן ירמיה ve'al zeh konen Yirmeyah this is
actually interesting because this is the first expression of sort of saying
God where are you? Like the sort of the whole theme of
the קינות kinot God how could you let this happen? Like this
is like the sort of a little bit you had a tiny
little echo of it or little hint of it before when the
גמרא Gemara said before right מי כמוכה באלים ה' mi kamocha ba'eilim
Hashem like who is amongst the gods that can remain silent. But
here you actually have like somebody actually calling God and challenging God
as it were saying how could you let this happen? So ועל
זה כונן ירמיה ve'al zeh konen Yirmeyah בתי עמי חגרי שק biti
ami chagri sak daughter of my nation wear a sackcloth והתפלשי באפר
vehitpalshi be'afar and you know cover yourself in dust. אבל יחיד עשי
לך eivel yachid asi lach make for yourself a mourning of a
private mourning מספד תמרורים misped tamrurim a bitter a bitter crying and
eulogizing. כי פתאום יבוא השודד עלינו ki pitom yavo hashoded aleinu suddenly
will the captor come upon us.
Now this is by the way God talking right בתי עמי חגרי
שק biti ami chagri sak right?
So presumably this is in the voice of God and it said
the שודד shoded will suddenly come upon us. So עליך לא נאמר
alecha lo ne'emar on you it doesn't say אלא עלינו ela aleinu
on us כי כביכול עלי ועליך ki kavyachol alai ve'alecha on me
and on you that it's something that I myself God am being
right you know hurt by this afflicted by the affliction that you
are suffering. Okay so that's you know God like עמו אנכי בצרה
imo anochi betzarah but then the question is how God can you
not defend your own your own name here and allow this to
happen בשודד. bashoded. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב Amar Rav Yehudah amar
Rav מאי דכתיב mai dichtiv
what's meant by the פסוק ועשקו גבר וביתו ve'ashku gever uveito and
they will oppress a man and his household ואיש ונחלתו ve'ish venachalato
a man and his inheritance. מעשה באדם אחד maaseh be'adam echad
so now again this is so interesting right because you have this
what we're going to see and what you have in the קינות
kinot as well is the shifting from challenging God God how could
you let this happen but also that's a very audacious type of
a religious statement. So and then there's always like it also often
gets softened a little bit or you know counter-parted by like oh
but we have sinned you know. It happens in איכה Eicha as
well like there's a most of איכה is God how could you
let this happen but then there's some פסוקים that pull back and
say you know oh you know this happened to us כי לא
שמענו לו ki lo shamanu lo because we did not listen to
Him and we did not you know we did not heed. You
had that before right by the guy in prison right that he
quoted the beginning of the פסוק and the response back was the
end of the פסוק that this is because we did not listen
to God and we did not follow in God's ways. So here
too you're getting this happening which is right after this story about
God how could you let this happen we're going to see you
know terrible sin you know that can explain to some degree you
know or somehow you know fits into the classic שכר ועונש s'char
va'onesh type of framework that we usually have. So it's sort of
the shifting back and forth between these two models. Not being able
to comprehend it and then going back to but look at how
we sinned. Okay so what does this פסוק what does this
mean? מעשה באדם אחד, ma'aseh be-adam echad, a certain man שנתן עיניו
באשת רבו. she-naton einav be-eishet rabbo. He lusted after his master's wife.
ושוליא דנגרי הוה, veshulya de-nagari hava, and he was a
carpenter's apprentice. פעם אחת הוצרך ללוות. pa'am achat hutźrach lilvot.
One time apparently he had more money at least available cash than
his master did. So his master needed some money. אמר לו, amar
lo, so he was going to borrow from his apprentice. So the
apprentice said to him, שגר אשתך אצלי, shagar ishtecha etzli, send your
wife to me, and I'll lend her the money and she can
bring it back to you. שיגר אשתו אצלו, shiger ishto etzlo, he
sent his wife, ושהתה עמו שלושה ימים. veshahatah immo sheloshah yamim.
So he spent three days with her. Now were they actually having
sex, or what did it mean that he had her wait for
three days and said I have to collect the funds? Okay, one
way or the other way, he's going to use the fact that
it took her three days as a we'll see to make trouble.
Okay, so she took
three days she was there. קדם ובא אצלו, kadam u-va etzlo,
and then this apprentice came to his
master. He bumped into him. אמר לו, amar lo, so the master
said אשה ששיגרתי לך היכן היא? ishah she-shigarti lecha heichan hi? What
happened to my wife? אמר לו, amar lo, he said to him,
אני פטרתיה לאלתר, ani petartiah le-altar, I don't know, I lent her
the money right away, as she came to me I lent her
the money, I said goodbye. I don't know where she's been the
last three days. ושמעתי, ve-shamati, but what I heard
is שהתינוקות נתעללו בה בדרך, she-ha-tinokot nit'allu bah ba-derech, that when she
was going back, the now it's interesting, the תינוקות, tinokot, right, because
sometimes I mean usually like, but here it means like the young
and by context it must mean the young men
had sport with her on the way. Now again that's funny because
the verse before להיתעלל, lehit'allel, right, you know obviously means like sexual
you know is about sex, but often it means to essentially to
rape, like you know and that's what certainly the sense before about
that beautiful woman that was taken by the captor and so on.
But here from the context it's going to mean that she basically
has been cheating on you for the last three days. Okay, so
we're going to see it doesn't just mean that she was
raped and taken advantage of. אמר לו, amar lo, so he said
to him מה אעשה? mah e'eseh? What can I do? אמר לו,
amar lo, he said back to him אם אתה שומע לעצתי, im
attah shome'a la-atzati, listen to me, גרשה, garsheh, just divorce her. אמר
לו, amar lo, he said to him כתובתה מרובה, ketubatah merubbah,
no her כתובה ketubah is too big, I can't afford to divorce
her. אמר לו, amar lo, he said אני אלווך, ani alvecha, I'll
lend you, don't worry, I'll lend you the money, ותן לה כתובתה,
ve-ten lah ketubatah, and you can pay her כתובה ketubah off. עמד
זה וגירשה, amad zeh ve-gershah, so the master there divorced his wife.
הלך הוא ונשאה, halach hu ve-nesa'ah,
so then he went and he married her. כיון שהגיע זמנו ולא
היה לו לפורעו, keivan she-higgia zemanno ve-lo hayah lo le-for'o,
and then it was time to pay up the debt for the
money he borrowed for the כתובה, ketubah, but the master didn't have
the money to pay for the כתובה. ketubah. So אמר לו, amar
lo, בוא ושמשני בחובך, bo u-shamsheni be-chovcha,
fine, you want to pay off your debt? Come and be my
slave, be my servant. והיו הם יושבים ואוכלים, ve-hayu hem yoshvim ve-ochlim,
so he and his new wife now were sitting and eating, ושותים,
ve-shotim, and rejoicing, והוא, ve-hu, and the master היה עומד ומשקה עליהן,
hayah omed u-mashkeh aleihen, was having to stand there and attend to
them and pour their wine for them. והיו דמעות נושרות מעיניו ונופלות
בכוסיהן, ve-hayu dema'ot nosherot me-einav ve-nofelot be-choseihen,
and his eyes would pour from his eyes and fall into their
cups. ובאותה שעה נחתם גזר דין, u-ve-otah sha'ah nechtam gezar din, and
at that moment was when the seal of their judgment was when
their judgment was sealed, that they would like be destroyed. Now is
this the בית המקדש beit ha-mikdash would be destroyed, or meant a
person used to be like explaining not just these people but like
you know the people in general, the society had become so corrupt,
this is symbolic of the corruption of the society and that's when
it was decided okay, there's no going back from this. Society's so
corrupt and so on and this is a different tone of course
than the בית המקדש beit ha-mikdash story. The בית המקדש beit ha-mikdash
story started with an interpersonal thing, קמצא ובר קמצא, kamtsa u-var kamtsa,
but it's very much also got very quickly into בית המקדש. beit
ha-mikdash. You know you had the rabbis, you had bringing a קרבן
korban and so on. Here we've been dealing with a page and
a half about the destruction of the population, and on the one
hand you remember we had these beautiful scenes of this like very
quaint traditional ways about the chicken and the rooster and the cedar
tree and so on and like you know so it was this
beautiful society that was destroyed. But here you sort of to try
to make some sense of it, talking about how corrupt the society
had become. Of course who's to say this just wasn't one corrupt
individual, but it's being used to symbolize how corrupt they had become.
One minute. ואמרי לה על שתי פתילות בנר אחד, ve-amrei lah al
shetei petilot be-ner echad, and some say no the final מכה בפטיש
makkah be-pattish as we would say was literally this means two wicks
in one candle which basically means when a woman started marrying two
men. Okay, so society become so corrupt and again interestingly you know
sexual corruption but also taking advantage you know
of people in a vulnerable situation and so on. So that's some
explanation of how this could all have been allowed to have happened.
Yes.
A lot of these depressing narratives are related to the same אמורא
amora רב יהודה. rav yehudah.
Oh that's interesting. So maybe he was very interested in trying to
give some theological explanation for all of this. Right, it is interesting
yes.
My תוספות tosafot says the בר קמצא bar kamtsa did know here's
a מהרש"א maharsha in the גמרא שבת gemara shabbat that says it's
well-known.
Right, so that's a way of making it—so I was sort of
saying this was the first cluster. Yes. Now, the same way בר
קמצא Bar Kamtza said the Rabbis didn't say anything, right. So yeah,
clearly, so you could assume that context as—but either way, it certainly
sounds like this is symbolic of what was so corrupt about the
whole society. Okay. So now, we are done with the אגדתא Agadata
about the—about the חורבן הבית. Churban Habayit. And now we get back
to the משנה, Mishna, okay. So לקח מן הסיקריקון. Lakach Min Hasikrikon.
So that was an interesting digression, but then it's like, okay, can
we get back to some הלכה? Halacha? Okay, לקח מן הסיקריקון. Lakach
Min Hasikrikon. I don't know how—whatever. It's good, but like we gotta—time
to move on. Okay. So get back. לקח מן הסיקריקון. Lakach Min
Hasikrikon. אמר רב: Amar Rav: so this is got you buy from
the—at this time after the חורבן הבית Churban Habayit when people are
forcing—these Romans or whatever forcing the Jews to sell their land, but
in theory, the Jews could actually sue them in court. So then
to what degree does this person who sees the land owns it
and sells it and speaks about you have to buy it from
him and buy it from the Jew and buy it in the
right order so we don't assume the Jew is just selling it
to you so that he doesn't get in trouble with the סיקריקון
Sikrikon and so on. So אמר רב, Amar Rav, לא שנו אלא
דאמר לו לך חזק וקני. Lo shanu ela de'amar lo lech chazek
ukeni. When is it that if you buy from the Jew after
the סיקריקון Sikrikon it's not binding because we assume he only—he didn't
really want to sell it to you, he only gave it to
you so he didn't get in trouble with the סיקריקון? Sikrikon? If
he just verbally says to you, fine, go and take possession of
it. אבל בשטר, Aval beshtar, if he actually wrote out a document
of sale, then קנה, kana, then you do buy possession, because that
shows that he really is intending to sell to you even if
he did it only after you bought it from the סיקריקון. Sikrikon.
ושמואל אמר, U'Shmuel amar, אף בשטר נמי לא קנה עד שיכתוב לו
אחריות. af beshtar nami lo kana ad sheyichtov lo achrayut. Even by
a שטר shtar it doesn't work unless in the שטר shtar you
actually write
a—liability. I'm selling you this land, and if anybody takes it from
you and seizes it from you, I will compensate you for it.
So if you go out of the way to write your liability
into the document, your insurance in the document, clearly you must really
mean to sell it. Okay, so in that case, even if you
bought it from the Jew after the סיקריקון, Sikrikon, he really meant
to sell it. תניא כוותיה דשמואל: Tanya kavatei d'Shmuel: we taught like
שמואל. Shmuel. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר: Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer:
לקח מן האשה וחזר ולקח מן האיש. Lakach min ha'isha v'chazar v'lakach
min ha'ish. So this same idea about which order you buy it
from and the second person really means to sell it, it's the
סיקריקון Sikrikon and the original owner, and it's also the husband and
wife about property that the woman has a lien on for her
כתובה. ketubah. So if you buy from the wife after the husband,
we say she didn't really want to sell it, she was only
doing it not to get in trouble with her husband, to make
her husband happy. So לקח מן
האשה וחזר ולקח מן האיש, Lakach min ha'isha v'chazar v'lakach min ha'ish,
first from the wife and then the husband, מקחו קיים, mekachu kayam,
it's good. מן האיש וחזר ולקח מן האשה, Min ha'ish v'chazar v'lakach
min ha'isha,
first from the husband and then the wife, מקחו בטל, mekachu batel,
it's not valid because the wife did not really want to sell
it to you. עד—but Ad when would it be good? שיכתוב לו
אחריות. sheyichtov lo achrayut. If she writes a שטר shtar and puts
in it that she assumes liability for compensation, then it is good
even if you bought it from the wife after the husband. So
נימא תהוי תיובתא דרב? nima tehvei tiyuvta d'Rav? This is a contradiction
to רב, Rav it shows that a שטר shtar isn't enough, needs
אחריות. achrayut. אמר לך רב: Amar lach Rav: no, מאי אחריות נמי
שטר. mai achrayut nami shtar. No, אחריות achrayut means you wrote a
שטר, shtar, and therefore רש"י: why does that mean אחריות? achrayut? So
רש"י says because it doesn't mean a lien on your property, that's
not what אחריות achrayut means, but it means that it makes it
binding, it makes it final. תוספות Tosafot however says that maybe the
debate of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel is whether you need to
write אחריות achrayut explicitly in a document or not or whether it's
implied. So רב might be saying any שטר shtar has אחריות achrayut
implied in it, and that's why you don't need to write it
and that's why that's what the word אחריות achrayut means. Okay. תנו
רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: לקח מן הסיקריקון ואכלה שלש שנים בפני בעלים, Lakach
min hasikrikon v'achala shalosh shanim bifnei be'alim, וחזר ומכרה לאחר. v'chazar u'mcharah
l'acher. אין לבעלים על לוקח שני כלום. Ein labe'alim al lokeach sheni
klum.
Now,
we you went ahead and you purchased it from the סיקריקון, Sikrikon,
okay, and so
one minute, right, right, one minute, let me just check one thing.
Right. So basically what happens is
that you went ahead and one person bought it from the סיקריקון.
Sikrikon. Now as we know, this is still stage one of the
תקנה. takana. He had to after buying it from the סיקריקון, Sikrikon,
or actually before buying it from the סיקריקון, Sikrikon, he had to
go ahead and buy it from the בעל הבית, ba'al habayit, or
he had to buy from the בעל הבית, ba'al habayit, and now
we're learning the בעל הבית—the ba'al habayit original owner could sell it
to him with a שטר, shtar, okay. But it would not suffice
to buy it from the סיקריקון. Sikrikon. So this man bought it
from the סיקריקון. Sikrikon. We don't know if he also purchased it
legitimately from the בעל הבית. ba'al habayit. And then he turned around
and sold that land to a third party, okay. לקח מן הסיקריקון
ואכלה שלש שנים בפני בעלים. Lakach min hasikrikon v'achala shalosh shanim bifnei
be'alim.
I'm sorry. First he ate—he ate the produce for three years, and
the owner knew he was eating the produce. Now some of you
might know that the הלכה halacha in בבא בתרא Bava Batra is
is that if you've been on somebody's property for three years and
then they come and say to you, "What are you doing on
my property?" and you say, "Oh, I bought it from you," and
he says, "Oh yeah? Show me the document," you could say, "I
don't need to show you the document of sale. Like you don't
have to save your receipts, you know, your back tax or whatever.
How—what is it, is it three years? How long do you have
to save your receipts? Anyway, you don't have to." Seven years. What?
The חזקה Chazakah is that if you've been on somebody's property for
three years and then they come and say to you, "What are
you doing on my property?" and you say, "Oh, I bought it
from you," and he says, "Oh yeah? Show me the document," you
could say, "I don't need to show you the document of sale."
You don't have to save your receipts, your back tax or whatever.
What is it? Is it three years? What? In any case, it's
three years. Anyway, you don't have to save them beyond three years.
You could say, "You saw me, you saw me here, you didn't
make any claims against you, I was therefore free to throw away
my receipts after three years." Okay, so after three years you can
say, "I don't need a שטר Shtar because I can say that
I lost it." Okay, so that's הלכה Halacha of חזקה. Chazakah. So
here, you bought it from the סיקריקון. Sikrikon. We don't know if
you bought it from the בעל הבית, Baal Habayit, what we do
know is you've been eating it for three years in the presence
of the בעל הבית. Baal Habayit. Okay, and if you were to
claim after three years, "I bought it from you and I don't
have the שטר," Shtar, you'd be believed. Okay, and then what did
you do? וחזר ומכרה לאחר—you V'chazar umcharah l'acher sold it to a
third party. אין לבעלים על לוקח שני כלום. Ein l'baalim al lokeach
sheni klum. The original owners can't make any claims against the person
who purchased it. So the גמרא Gemara says, היכי דמי, Heichi Dami,
what's the case? אי דקא טעין ואמר מינך
זבנתה—if Ei dek'a ta'in v'amar minech zavnitah the guy who bought it
from the סיקריקון Sikrikon is saying to the original owner, "I bought
it from you, I don't have the שטר Shtar anymore, it's been
three years," so אפילו ראשון נמי—so Afilu rishon nami why do we
have to say that the third party is safe? Even the original
purchaser is safe, right? Because it's been three years and he's saying
that he bought it and he doesn't have the שטר. Shtar. אי
דלא קא טעין—if Ei d'lo k'a ta'in he's not making a claim
that he bought it, he's saying, "I never bought it from you,
but I've been here three years," so he's not making that claim,
and if he's not claiming he bought it from the original owner,
אפילו שני נמי לא—then Afilu sheni nami lo how could the purchaser
keep the land? Right? If the original guy is not claiming that
he actually bought it from the owner. Is that clear? Right? So
with the three years, he's believed to say he bought it from
the owner. But then he'd be believed even if he hadn't sold
it yet, even if we weren't talking about the third party. And
if he wasn't making that claim, why would the third party be
believed? So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Sheshet,
לעולם דלא קא טעין ליה. L'olam d'lo k'a ta'in lei. He is
not, the guy who bought the land from the סיקריקון Sikrikon is
not making any claim. He's not around or he says, "Leave me
out of this," whatever it is. Okay. And the guy who purchased
it doesn't know enough what he's supposed to say in בית דין.
Beis Din. He's like, "Huh? What? I just bought this land from
this guy." Oh no, now the original owner is coming and saying
it's like, "I don't know what I'm supposed to say to defend
myself." So we come and we assist him and we say, "Here's
the claim you have to make. You have to say to him,
'The first guy who sold it to me bought it from you,
and he doesn't need to prove it because he's been there for
three years.'" So you, the guy who purchased the land from the
guy who got it from the סיקריקון—you're Sikrikon the third party, right?
You don't know what to say, but we prompt you and tell
you that the way you're going to win this case is by
claiming that the guy you bought it from bought it from the
original owner and doesn't have to prove it because he's been there
for three years. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, לעולם דלא קא
טעין ליה, L'olam d'lo k'a ta'in lei, that no, the original guy
who purchased it from the סיקריקון... Sikrikon... Maybe we need names. Is
it clear who's who in this story?
No, that's confusing. Are you confused?
Okay, I'm sorry. I needed to give names of first guy, second
guy. Okay. ראובן, Reuven, שמעון, Shimon, and לוי. Levi. Alright. ראובן Reuven
was the
סיקריקון... Sikrikon... No, we don't need the סיקריקון Sikrikon in this story.
Where's ראובן? Reuven?
Okay. Here's ראובן. Reuven.
ראובן Reuven was the original owner, okay? He's the original.
Okay. Here's the סיקריקון Sikrikon with the land. סיקריקון. Sikrikon. סיקריקון. Sikrikon.
Okay. שמעון Shimon
bought the land from the סיקריקון. Sikrikon. And now he eats it
three years. Okay. Now, if שמעון, Shimon, we know he had to
also buy it from ראובן, Reuven, right? That we know from the
משנה. Mishnah. After he's been there three years, he can just be
believed to say he bought it from ראובן Reuven and he doesn't
have the שטר. Shtar. But if he doesn't say he bought it
from ראובן, Reuven, he just says, "No, I didn't buy it from
you, but I've been here three years." Well, you didn't buy it
from him, you've got to give it back to him. Three years
doesn't work. Three years is a way of backing up a claim
that I bought it from you. Okay. Comes לוי Levi and לוי
Levi buys the field from שמעון. Shimon. And the גמרא Gemara says,
לוי Levi is believed. So the גמרא Gemara says, "One minute. If
שמעון Shimon is claiming that he bought it from ראובן Reuven and
the three years back it up, then שמעון Shimon is believed. You
don't have to move on to לוי. Levi. And if שמעון Shimon
is not making the claim that he bought it from ראובן, Reuven,
then לוי Levi doesn't work. It doesn't help לוי Levi either. It
has to have been bought from ראובן." Reuven. So the גמרא Gemara
is saying we don't know what שמעון Shimon is doing. שמעון Shimon
isn't around. שמעון Shimon is not making any claim. So לוי Levi
now, ראובן Reuven is coming to לוי Levi and saying, "Give me
back my
field." לוי Levi doesn't know what to
say. "All I know is I bought it from שמעון." Shimon. He
doesn't know שמעון Shimon three years, what does that mean? He doesn't
know what to say. So we prompt לוי Levi and we say,
"לוי, Levi, here's what you've got to say to ראובן. Reuven. Say
to him, 'שמעון Shimon must have bought it from you and he
doesn't have the שטר Shtar and he doesn't need to prove it
because he's been there for three years.'" So we feed that claim
to לוי Levi to help him protect himself against ראובן, Reuven, okay?
And that's what we do. Is that clear? Yes? Okay. If לוי
Levi just said, "I don't know," we would say, "Well, he never
bought it from you." No, no, no. Here's what you say. Say
he must have bought it from you and he doesn't have the
שטר. Shtar. It's been three years. Okay.
Can someone force ראובן Reuven off that land before three years? Yeah.
Even if he didn't have a שטר? Shtar? No, if he had
a שטר Shtar he couldn't have. Yeah, because if you buy from
the סיקריקון Sikrikon you still have to still purchase it from the
original owner. So if he didn't have a שטר, Shtar, what?
Does the same apply for ירושה?
Yerushah? Yes, and that's actually what the גמרא Gemara is going to
say. ועולם דלא טענינן כגון זה טענינן ליורש וטענינן ללוקח. Ve'olam delo
tainan kegon zeh tainan leyores vetainan lelo'keach.
We will provide the the right claim, you know, defense for for
either an heir or for a purchaser. They don't know, somebody's saying
your father stole this land from me, it's not his or whatever,
the guy who sold it to you, and they don't we realize
that they're supposed to say he was there three years, so there's
no might not be any documentation, but we don't need documentation, we
can assume he bought it from you, okay? ואידך אי טען אין
אי לא לא. Ve'idach ei ta'an in ei lo lo. But the
original guy, שמעון, Shimon, שמעון's Shimon got to defend himself. If שמעון
Shimon was the one who was being challenged, he has to be
able to say I bought it from you. And if he can't
say I bought it from you, then we've got a problem, okay?
But לוי Levi doesn't know, for לוי Levi we provide that טענה.
Taina. All right. Let's
let's try to read, we have two minutes, so let's try to
read at least another two lines. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabbanan. הבא מחמת
חוב ומחמת אנפרות אין בו משום סיקריקון. Haba machmas hov umachmas amparut
ein bo mishum sikrikon. If somebody is if land was seized for
a debt or was just stolen, but not stolen because your life
was being threatened, so not the Roman seized it for debts or
they just stole the land, you don't have the סיקריקון Sikrikon law,
okay? ואנפרות עצמו צריכה שתשהא שנים עשר חודש. Ve'amparut atzmo tzricha shetisheh
shneim asar chodesh. And for the case of the theft itself, you
need twelve months. Now what does the סיקריקון Sikrikon law mean? Here
we're dealing with the law at stage two. You remember the law
at stage two was that afterwards they said, you know what, after
the סיקריקון Sikrikon has it, you don't have to buy it again
from the בעל הבית, Baal habayis, like the בעל הבית Baal habayis
has given up hope after twelve months, we can assume the בעל
הבית Baal habayis has given up hope getting it back and it
belongs to the סיקריקון, Sikrikon, just give the בעל הבית Baal habayis
a quarter of the value, okay? Remember that was the stage two
of the תקנה. Takana. So he's saying that stage that idea that
you don't have to buy it again from the בעל הבית, Baal
habayis, we assume he just he gave up hope after twelve months,
that only applies when it was a סיקריקון, Sikrikon, his life was
at he was his life was being threatened. But if it's in
something else being seized in a debt or seized out of theft
or whatever, just simple case of theft, then we don't assume that
he's given up hope of getting it back and you it's never
sufficient to buy it from the סיקריקון. Sikrikon. Okay, so that's the
law, there's no law of סיקריקון. Sikrikon. But then he says, oh,
but by the case of theft, it needs twelve months. So the
גמרא Gemara says what do you mean it needs twelve months? You
just said this law doesn't apply. גמרא Gemara says אמרת אין בו
משום סיקריקון, Amarta ein bo mishum sikrikon, the law of סיקריקון Sikrikon
doesn't apply, that's the twelve months law. הכי קאמר. Hachi ka'amar.
סיקריקון עצמו צריכה שתשהא י"ב חודש. Sikrikon atzmo tzricha shetisheh yud beis
chodesh. אנפרות Amparut doesn't have the law of סיקריקון Sikrikon and the
סיקריקון Sikrikon law is that you have to wait twelve months and
after twelve months you can buy it from the סיקריקון. Sikrikon. That
was stage two of the law. But that law only applies to
a סיקריקון, Sikrikon, not to a simple case of debt or just
simple theft. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, one more line, נקטינן
Naktinan we take the position אין אנפרות בבבל. Ein amparut beBavel. That
there is no of these cases of theft of land in בבל.
גמרא Gemara says what do you mean? הא קחזינן דאיכא, Ha kach
hazinan de'ika, people do steal land. אלא אימא אין דין אנפרות בבבל.
Ela eima ein din amparut beBavel.
There's no law of אנפרות Amparut which means
that you cannot say, oh, it was stolen from me and it's
still mine and I didn't give up hope of getting it back.
No, if somebody seized it, you you cannot make a legitimate claim,
oh, it was stolen and you can't purchase it from that person.
Why? This is very interesting. It says something about what happens when
you have a functioning and trustworthy legal system. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama?
כיון דאיכא בי דואר, Keivan de'ika bei davar, since there's a court
system, ולא אזיל קביל, Velo azil kavel,
and you did not go and register a claim in that court
system, אמחולי אחיל, Amachulei achlei,
so it must be that you have made peace with it, that
you somehow have like waived any claims against the land. So somebody,
some you know, Babylonian, whatever, Persian, seizes your land and you could
make a claim, it's a system in which you have, you know,
you can you can make a claim, it's a right, it's a
good it's a good legal system in place, okay? And you don't
make a claim, then that's going to then we can presume that
he has right he's rightfully possessing the land and somebody's entitled to
purchase it off with him. What? They had faith in that system,
exactly. More faith that they had in that system than they had
in the Roman system, you know, or at least but now the
point is the Roman system might have been just, but they gave